RESUME

Didier Augusto Vega-Oliveros

davo@icmc.usp.br

For more information visit https://didiervega.github.io

PROFILE

Postdoctoral Research Fellow (FAPESP) at the Department of Computer Science, University of São Paulo – USP and research collaborator at Brazilian National Institute of Space Research (INPE). He has experience in Artificial Intelligence and Machine learning applied to Big Data systems for high-scalability. He holds a B.Sc degree in Computer and Systems Engineer from Universidad Nacional de Colombia and received his Masters and Ph.D. in Computer Science and Computational Mathematics at Universidade de São Paulo, Brazil. He was visiting researcher at Northeastern University, USA, under the supervision of Dr. Albert-Lázló Barabási; at Universidad de la Plata, Argentina, working with Dr. Federico Vazquez; and at Humboldt University of Berlin, Germany, in an international project led by Dr. Jürgens Kurths. He has participated in projects applied to industry and society, employing Computational Intelligence and Machine Learning methods for Big Data analysis, proposing scalable solutions with distributed, parallel and cloud computing systems. His research experience includes the study of Ubiquitous Computing, User-Computer Interaction (HCI) and multimodal interfaces for the development of intelligent systems. He also worked on research related to Complex Networks theory and their dynamical processes, such as the spreading of epidemics, rumors or opinions on social networks. Currently, his fields of interests encompass Machine Learning based on Complex Networks in the modeling of Climate systems for disasters risk reduction and management, and social networks analysis.

EDUCATION / TITLES

• 2017 - 2019 Postdoctoral research fellow

Project: Dynamical processes in complex network based on machine learning

Advisor: <u>Zhao Liang</u> Advisor: <u>Elbert E. N. Macau</u>

Supported by São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP)

Univeristy of Sao Paulo – USP and National Institute of Space Research – INPE, Brazil

• 2013 – 2017 PhD in Computer Science

Title: Rumors and Information Spreading on Social Networks

Supervisor: <u>Francisco Aparecido Rodrigues</u> Co- Supervisor: <u>Luciano da Fontoura Costa</u>

Scholarship from National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq)

Univeristy of Sao Paulo - USP, Brazil

• 2009 – 2011 MSc in Computer Science

Title: Media-Oriented Operators for Authoring Multimedia Documents: Interactors

Supervisor: Maria da Graça Campos Pimentel

Scholarship from National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq)

Univeristy of Sao Paulo - USP, Brazil

• 2003 – 2008 Bachelor's degree in Computer Engineering

Title: Mobile Virtual Network Operators (MVNOs) and Potential Actors in Colombia

Supervisor: Zoila Inés Ramos de Florez

National University of Colombia, Bogotá, D.C., Colombia

COMPLEMENTARY FORMATION

 2017 Research Visitor at Humboldt University of Berlin, Germany Invited by: <u>Jürgens Kurths</u>
Supported by DFG-IGRK 1740/2 and FAPESP 2015/50122-0 joint project

• 2016 Research Visitor at National University of La Plata, Argentina

Advisor: Federico Vázquez

Supported by Santander Scholarship award

• 2014 Visiting Scholar at Center for Complex Network Research (CCNR)

Advisor: Albert-László Barabási

Northeastern University, United States of America

• 2008 **Undergraduate Exchange Student** at Institute of Mathematics and Computer Sciences (ICMC) Advisor: Maria da Graça Campos Pimentel

Univeristy of Sao Paulo - USP, Brazil

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Currently with 20 academic works published

Google Scholar citations 79, h-index 6, i10-index 4

Berton, L.; Lopes, A. A.; Vega-Oliveros, D. A A Comparison of Graph Construction Methods for Semi-Supervised Learning. In: International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN), 2018, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.	
Vega-Oliveros, D. A.; Berton, L.; Vazquez, F. Rodrigues, Rodrigues, F. A The Impact of Social Curiosity on Information Spreading on Networks. In: IEEE/ACM International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM), 2017, Sydney, Australia, v. 0. p. 459-466.	Cited by 1
Vega-Oliveros, D. A.; Costa, Luciano da F.; Rodrigues, F. A. Rumor propagation with heterogeneous transmission in social networks. Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory and Experiment, v. 2017, n. 2, p. 023401.	Cited by 13
Berton, L.; Vega-Oliveros, D. A.; Valverde-Rebaza, J. C.; da Silva A. T.; Lopes, A. A. The Impact of Network Sampling on Relational Classification. In: 3rd Annual International Symposium on Information Management and Big Data (SIMBig), 2016, Cusco, Peru, p. 62-72.	Cited by 2
Vega-Oliveros, D. A.; Berton, L.; Lopes, A. A.; Rodrigues, F. A. Influence maximization based on the least influential spreaders. In: International Workshop on Social Influence Analysis (SocInf). 24th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), 2015, Buenos Aires, Argentina, p. 3-8.	Cited by 5
Vega-Oliveros, D. A.; Berton, L. Spreader Selection by Community to Maximize Information Diffusion in Social Networks. In: 2nd Annual International Symposium on Information Management and Big Data (SIMBig), 2015, Cusco, Peru, p. 73-82.	Cited by 2
Vega-Oliveros, D. A.; Berton, L.; Eberle, A. M.; Lopes, A. A.; Zhao, L. Regular graph construction for semi-supervised learning. Journal of Physics. Conference Series (Online), 2014, v. 490, p. 012022.	Cited by 10
Vega-Oliveros, D. A.; Martíns, D. S.; Pimentel, M. G. P. Media-oriented operators for authoring interactive multimedia documents generated from capture sessions. In: ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), 2011, TaiChung. Proceedings of the 2011 ACM Symposium on Applied	Cited by 7

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

02/2017 – 06/2017 University Herminio Ometto, UNIARARAS, Brazil. – Faculty of Engineering
Assistant Professor at Faculty of Engineering teaching the courses of: Computer Programming I (classes A and B) and Computer Programming III (classes A, B, C, D, E, and G).

• 05/2011 - 01/2013 Invit Information Services – R&D team of Intelligence Agents and Semantic Framework

Agentto project (<u>www.agentto.com</u>**):** Design and development of a Semantic Framework and intelligent agents for the processing of contextual data to conduct queries and inferences about high-level events of context and situation awareness, with modules projected to high scalability and performance in both the cloud and clients.

04/2012 Software Architect: Promoted to technical leader who coordinates the Semantic Framework team

Main activities:

- ✓ Coordination and planning of team activities
- ✓ Management the deployment of cloud applications
- Architect and developer in the clients of a security alarm system activated by slaps (feature running in production)
- ✓ Developer and designer of PTT (push-to-talk) infrastructure, client libraries and interface (feature running in production)
- ✓ Architect and developer of a semantic framework based on ontologies and reasoning
- ✓ Leader of research and adoption of CEP (Complex Event Processing), Semantic Web, Ubiquitous and Pervasive Computing, Context-Awareness and Situation-Awareness.
- Management and planning of functional and nonfunctional tests

05/2011 **Software Engineer**: Developer and designer in an interdisciplinary team for creating new product feature Main activities:

- ✓ Proposal of agents architecture based on CEP (Complex Event Processing)
- ✓ Developer in both server and client (Android and Windows Phone 7) of the protocol to communicate with the cloud (feature running in production)
- ✓ Developer and designer of a feature that infers user's frequent places (running in production)
- ✓ Design and development of abstraction layer for data persistence in various types of Azure storage
- ✓ Design and development of product feature in Windows Phone and Android

- ✓ Deployment of applications in Cloud Computing
- ✓ Applied research, in combination with the Federal University of Uberlândia, in the areas of Al, Context/Situation-Awareness, Multimodal and Natural Interfaces and Natural Language Processing
- ✓ Implementation of testing like unit and integration tests and performance, load and stress test
- Mitigation of technical risks for the adoption and integration of new cutting-edge technologies
- ✓ Participation in the implementation of SCRUM
- 03/2009 10/2009 Intermidia lab at ICMC/USP TIDIA-Ae project (<u>www.tidia-ae.usp.br</u>)

Software Engineer: Development of a player in NCLua and SMIL that enables the review and synchronization of captured data (chat session, video conferencing and electronic whiteboard) for the DiGaE tool (Distributed Gathering Environment) of the TIDIA-Sakai Project of University of Sao Paulo.

KNOWLEDGES AND TECHNICAL SKILLS

- ✓ Cloud Computing
- ✓ Back-end software architectures
- ✓ OpenMP/MPI
- ✓ Ontologies
- ✓ XML, JSON, REST, SOAP
- ✓ ClickOnce
- ✓ SCRUM
- ✓ DevOps
- ✓ Agile Methodologies
- ✓ TDD, Usability test
- ✓ Complex Networks
- ✓ Machine learning
- ✓ Ubiquitous computing
- ✓ Human Computer Interaction
- ✓ WindowsPhone7, Android

AWARDS

- 2016 **Student Travel Award from SoFiA** Latin American School on Data Analysis and Mathematical Modeling of Social Science, financed by CELFI Latin American Center for Interdisciplinary Training.
- 2016 Santander Scholarship for Academic Exchange Visit
- 2015 Student Travel Award from IJCAI International Joint Conferences on Artificial Intelligence.
- 2008 Undergraduate Exchange Student Scholarship National University of Colombia.